Guide to the Reuben L. and Marcionella V. Curtiss Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Reuben L. and Marcionella V. Curtiss papers
1942-1979
MS 853
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2.5
(6 boxes)
Correspondence between Reuben L. and Marcionella V. Curtiss during World War II when each was serving in the United States Army make up the bulk of the papers. Reuben L. Curtiss's letters are sent from various parts of the United States, Africa, India, and China. Marcionella V. Curtiss's letters reflect her service in Australia, New Guinea and the Philippine Islands. There is also a diary kept by Reuben L. Curtiss (1944-1945), and a biographical sketch written by Marcionella V. Curtiss in 1979.
Curtiss, Reuben Lucius, 1897-1978
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Reuben L. Curtiss, 1975.
Scope and Contents
The Reuben L. and Marcionella V. Curtiss Papers consist mainly of correspondence between Mr. and Mrs. Curtiss during their service in the United States Army in the Second World War. Mr. Curtiss wrote his letters mainly from army posts in the United States (September 1942-July 1943) and from India and China (August 1943-June 1945). Mrs. Curtiss wrote her letters from Milford, Connecticut (September-November 1942), from army posts in the United States (December 1942-June 1944), and from Australia, New Guinea, and the Philippines (June 1944-June 1945). The correspondence is most valuable for its descriptions and criticisms of army life and of the people and customs of the places in which the Curtisses were stationed. There is also a diary kept by Mr. Curtiss between February 1944 and December 1945.
The essential biographical source is a 3000-word letter that Mrs. Curtiss (now married to Leland Smith) wrote in February 1979 at the invitation of this department. It is boxed at the beginning of the papers. It not only provides information about parentage, schooling, employment, and the like, but also creates a vivid and moving impression of "Curt & Marcy - Their Life Together." This letter is essential to a full appreciation of the papers. For quick reference, however, please see the chronology selected from it in the Biographical Sketch above.
Biographical / Historical
1897 born in North Branford, Connecticut
[c. 1909] left school after the sixth grade
[1910s]-1942 held various jobs in New York City and Connecticut
1933 married Marcionella Vegas
1938 bought a campsite in Milford, Connecticut, and began living there except in the winters
1940 built a cabin on the Milford campsite and made it the Curtisses' permanent home
1942 joined the United States Army
1943-1945 served in India and China, supervising transport of American war materiel
1945 left the army
1945-[late 1950s] held various jobs in Connecticut
1952 fathered a son, Scott Dewitt
1978 died in the Veterans Administration Medical Center in West Haven, Connecticut
MARCIONELLA LILLYAN (VEGAS) CURTISS SMITH (1906-)
1914 born in Forteleza, Brazil, of American-born parents
1917 came to live in New York
[late 1920s] attended junior high school and one month of business school
[early 1930s] worked as a "girl friday" for Reuben Curtiss and attended high school in the evenings
1933 married Reuben Curtiss
1933-1942 held various jobs in New York City and Connecticut
1942 joined the United States Army
1944-1945 served in Australia, New Guinea, and the Philippines
1945 left the army
1945-1952 held various jobs in Connecticut
1952 gave birth to a son, Scott Dewitt
[late 1950s-late 1960s] held various jobs in Connecticut
1968 separated from Reuben Curtiss and went to live with his nephew, Leland Smith
1971 moved to the Southwest
1978 married Leland Smith
World War, 1939-1945 -- United States; Asia; Diaries; Soldiers; Curtiss, Reuben Lucius, 1897-1978; Smith, Marcionella Lillyan Vegas Curtiss, 1906-
- Inventory, 1942-1945, 1979; 2.5' (6 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  The Reuben L. and Marcionella V. Curtiss Papers were given to Yale University Library by Reuben L. Curtiss in 1975.
  - Marcionella V. Curtiss: biographical letter, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Reuben L. Curtiss: diary, 1944 February-1945 December (Box 1)
  - RLC to MVC
    - Fort Devens, Mass., 1942 September 1-4 (Box 1)
    - Atlantic City, N.J., 1942 September 6-24 (Box 1)
    - Madison, Wis., 1942 September 27-December 19 (Box 1)
    - en route to Florida, 1942 December 19-22 (Box 1)
    - Boca Raton, Fla, 1942 December 25-1943 February 7 (Box 1)
    - Las Vegas, N.M., 1943 February 8-March 31 (Box 1)
    - Las Vegas, N.M., 1943 April 1-10 (Box 2)
    - Billings, Mont., 1943 April 12-July 7 (Box 2)
    - Boca Raton, Fla., 1943 July 11-13 (Box 2)
    - Africa (en route to India), 1943 July 15-23 (Box 2)
    - Africa and Middle East (en route to India), 1943 July 24-31 (Box 2)
    - India (Karachi), 1943 August 1-October 13 (Box 2)
    - India (Chabua, Assam?), 1943 October 28-1944 February 24 (Box 2)
    - India (Ledo, Assam?), 1944 February 24-March 31 (Box 2)
    - India (Calcutta), 1944 April 1-September 9 (Box 3)
    - India (Panitola, Assam), 1944 September 16-27 (Box 3)
    - Kunming, China, 1944 September 30-1945 February 28 (Box 3)
    - Kunming, China, 1945 March 1-May 17 (Box 4)
    - Kunming, China, and Calcutta, India, 1945 May 18-June 16 (Box 4)
    - New Haven, Conn., 1945 July 25-27 (Box 4)
  - MVC to RLC
    - Milford, Conn., 1942 September 1-November 27 (Box 4)
    - en route to Iowa, 1942 November 28-29 (Box 4)
    - Des Moines, Iowa, 1942 December 2-1943 January 30 (Box 4)
    - Fort Knox, Ky., 1943 February 1-28 (Box 4)
    - Fort Knox, Ky., 1943 March 2-1944 April 19 (Box 5)
    - Milford, Conn., 1944 April 23-26 (Box 5)
    - Fort Oglethorpe, Ga., 1944 May 1-26 (Box 6)
    - en route to California, 1944 May 29-31 (Box 6)
    - California (San Francisco?), 1944 June 2-7 (Box 6)
    - en route to Australia, 1944 [June 8-25?] (Box 6)
    - Brisbane, Australia, 1944 June 26-October 22 (Box 6)
    - New Guinea, 1944 November 4-1945 January 28 (Box 6)
    - en route to the Philippines, 1945 [February 1-7?] (Box 6)
    - Philippines, 1945 February 8-April 7 (Box 6)
    - Philippines (Manila), 1945 April 17-June 4 (Box 6)
    - Clippings, undated (Box 6)